A Guide to the Ann A. Hertzler Collection, 1863-2013 (Bulk 1974-2000)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Ann A. Hertzler Collection, 1863-2013 (Bulk, 1974-2000)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Hertzler, Ann A., 1935-2014
Ms2001-004
An overview of materials from the Hertzler Collection available in digital format can be found online.
10.3 Cubic Feet 14 boxes; 1 oversize folder; 2 artifacts (on display)
The Ann A. Hertzler Collection contains biographical information, publications, project and subject files, and artifacts relating to Hertzler's professional career at the University of Missouri-Columbia (1974-1980) and Virginia Tech (1980-2001). Particular areas of emphasis are children's health and nutrition, food and food programs, and Extension publications from both colleges.
Adminstrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Materials in the Ann A. Hertzler Collection were donated in multiple accruals between 2001 and 2011. Additional materials were donated in 2014.
Alternate Form Available
An overview of materials from the Hertzler Collection available in digital format can be found online. Individual items are also linked to their online version in the contents list of the finding aid.
PDF versions of many Virginia Cooperative Extension publications, authored by Hertzler, are available online through VTechWorks here.
Biographical Note
In 1957, Ann A. Hertzler received a B.S. in Home Economics Education from Pennsylvania State University. She taught high school Home Economics for two years. In 1960, she completed a Master of Science in Nutrition at the Drexel Institute of Technology. Between 1960 and 1966, she taught at the Drexel Institute of Technology and Northern Illinois University, and spent a year as a dietitian in England. She then pursued a Ph.D. in Nutrition at Cornell University, completing her studies in 1973. From 1970 to 1980, Hertzler was a professor and Extension Specialist at the University of Missouri-Columbia. In 1980, she joined the faculty at Virginia Tech as a professor of Human Nutrition, Foods, and Exercise, and as a Foods and Nutrition Extension Specialist. She retired in 2001 and was granted Professor Emerita status. Dr. Hertzler died in 2014.
Throughout her extensive career, Ann A. Hertzler wrote numerous articles and presentations, many of which are represented in this collection. She wrote and revised many Virginia Cooperative Extension publications relating to, as well as developed resources for, adult's and children's nutrition. She received national and regional awards, including a Fulbright Scholarship in 1989-1990 and the American Dietetic Association's Award for Excellence in Dietetic Education (1999). Hertzler also worked with many national, regional, and local professional societies, especially the American Association for Families and Consumer Science, the Society for Nutrition Education, and the American Dietetic Association. In addition, she was involved in the development of the Peacock-Harper Culinary Collection at Virginia Tech Special Collections and served on M.S. and Ph.D. committees for students at the University of Missouri-Columbia and at Virginia Tech.
Scope and Content
The Ann A. Hertzler Collection contains biographical information, publications, project and subject files, and artifacts relating to Hertzler's professional career at the University of Missouri-Columbia (1974-1980) and Virginia Tech (1980-2001). Particular areas of emphasis are children's health and nutrition, food and food programs, and Extension publications from both colleges.
A majority of the publications and personal/professional material was originally contained in two 5-inch binders, which were broken down to facilitate integration with the rest of the collection. These binders included an introduction to the contents, as well as a brief overview of Hertzler's experiences and observations about changes to her field during her career. This introduction is included with the CV (Box-folder 1-1).
The collection is divided into 6 series--Series I: Curriculum Vita and Biographical Information, Series II: Hertzler Publications, Series III: Other Publications, Series IV: Project/Subject Files, Series V: Oversize Materials, and Series VI: Artifacts. Throughout the collection, folders containing publications include bibliographies--see the "Contents List" below.
This collection does not contain information relating to: the courses Hertzler taught at Virginia Tech or other schools; Hertzler's employment experience prior to the University of Missouri-Columbia; projects connected to service with the Virginia Dietetic Association; service in professional organizations; or sabbaticals taken in 1978 and 1989.
Arrangement
Series I: Curriculum Vita and Biographical Information, 1974-2001, contains a CV written in 2001. This folder also includes Hertzler's introduction to the binders mentioned above. The series also includes photocopies of awards Hertzler won, as well as related write-ups and correspondence. Lastly, there are photographs featuring Ann Hertzler from events, conferences, and newspapers articles (1970s-2000).
This series is arranged by material type. Awards are in chronological order. Photographs are, for the most part, on scrapbook pages, and are in their original order.
Series II: Hertzler Publications, 1971-2000, contains 6 subseries. The majority of this series is made up of subseries C and D. Some items have related correspondence attached. Subseries A: Articles includes copies, reprints, and originals of articles written by Hertzler during her tenure at the University of Missouri and Virginia Tech (1974-2000). This subseries does NOT include Extension Service publications. Subseries B: Contributions to Scholarly Works, 1976-2001, contains articles and photocopies of articles in which Hertzler is quoted or otherwise referenced. Subseries C: University of Missouri-Columbia Extension Publications includes handouts and pamphlets written by Hertzler (1971-1980, n.d.). This subseries also contains several publications from the early 1970s. Subseries D: Virginia Cooperative Extension Publications/Adult includes materials written and created by Hertzler relating to adult health and nutrition from 1982-2000. Subseries E: Virginia Cooperative Extension Publications/Children, 1985-1999, contains materials written and created by Hertzler relating to children's health and nutrition. Subseries F: Websites and Internet Information, 1997-2001, includes printouts of websites designed for Hertzler's various projects, as well as related correspondence and presentations.
Folder-level bibliographies are in the "Contents List" below. Subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by title. Material within each subseries is arranged in chronological order. Undated materials in Subseries III are arranged by publication number or publication title, if there is no number.
Series III: Other Publications, 1956-2000, includes 4 subseries. Subseries A: Articles and Reports, 1956-1998 contains publications written about children's nutrition, especially breakfast and school menu planning. Subseries B: Extension Services contains three publications from different state Extension divisions, written between 1979 and 1993. Subseries C: Pamphlets, 1965-1992, includes a selection of published materials created by national or international groups, a majority of which relate to diet restrictions and food choices. This subseries does NOT include materials produced by the U. S. Department of Agriculture. Subseries D: USDA includes pamphlets produced by the United States Department of Agriculture. Materials date from 1960 to 2000 and cover topics such as the importance of breakfast, food choices for children, and sodium intake.
Folder-level bibliographies are in the "Contents List" below. Subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by title. Materials within each subseries are arranged in chronological order.
Series IV: Project/Subject Files, 1982-2003, includes publications, correspondence and emails, copies of presentations, notes, and other paper materials relating to nutrition and health topics. In 2017, this series was organized into five subseries. Subseries A: Presentation and Project Materials contains materials from training programs on teaching children safe food handling habits, choosing healthy foods, and meal planning for child care facilities. In addition, this subseries includes VHS and audio cassette tapes from training events, and slides and CDs from presentations given by Ann Hertzler. Subseries B: Subject Files on Cooperative Extension and Nutrition Topics includes collected research from sources relating to children's nutrition, bone health, food labels, and Cooperative Extension activities. Subseries C: Subject Files on Food and People consists of collected researcher on individuals and groups of people connected to aspects of food history, including authors, other researchers, ethnic groups, and professionals. Subseries D: Subject Files on Foods includes collected research on foods or food groups used for papers, presentations, and personal interest. Subseries E: Subject Files on Home and Household contains research on household management topics, especially kitchen utensils and soap/soap-making.
Several files contain folder-level bibliographies in the contents list of the finding aid. Files in each subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
Series V: Posters and Oversize Books, 1989-1996, contains a poster of the human skeleton with labeled bones, a poster showing vegetables, and 3 copies of a book for children about nutrition and choosing healthy foods.
This series is arranged chronologically.
Series VI: Artifacts, c.1863, 1993, n.d., includes several original items--a stone jar from a battlefield, c. 1863, a gelatin mold, and a small sewing box. The series also has a framed display of a food pyramid and Happy Meal toys, produced by the American Dietetic Association and McDonalds in 1993. Dr. Hertzler also donated a 19th century cast iron stove to the libraries, which is in the Special Collections Reading Room. The 2014 accrual also includes a large collection of food-related magnets.
This series is arranged by material type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
In 2005, Professor Emerita Hertzler established the Ann Hertzler Children's Cookbook and Nutrition Literature Collection. Her initial donation of publications has grown to nearly 350 items dating from 1882 to 2007, most of which are housed in Special Collections. Additional publications are housed in the circulating collection at Newman Library. The Children's Cookbook and Nutrition Literature Collection is available through the library's online catalog. Books in this collection can be found by a keyword search of "Children's Cookbook and Nutrition Literature Collection."
Separated Materials
The following duplicate publications were removed from Series II: Hertzler Publications, Subseries IV and V: Virginia Cooperative Extension Publications, and cataloged for the Special Collections Rare Book Collection:
Hertzler, Ann A., and Phyllis Brown. February 1982. Cookouts and Cooking While Camping, Publication 348-010. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. May 1984. Potassium in the Diet, Publication 348-911. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. March 1985. Homemade Baby Food, Publication 348-012. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. January 1987. Cholesterol in the Diet, Publication 348-909. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. August 1987. Sodium in the Diet, Publication 348-910. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. October 1987. Kids, Food, and Money, Publication 348-007. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann, Valya Vincell, Janet Tuckwiller, Kathleen Stadler, Katherine Sharman, and Martha Durst. 1988. Let's Start Eating Smart, Publication 348-650. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. 1993. Sugar, Publication 348-013. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A., Mick Coleman, and Elaine D. Scott. 1993. Kids, Food, and Television, Publication 348-008. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Debord, Karen, and Ann A. Hertzler. 1993. Developmentally Appropriate Food and Nutrition Skills for Young Children, Publication 348-651. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A., and Karen DeBord. 1993. Kids Cart Smart Food Choices at Home, Shopping, and Eating Out, Publication 348-652. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A., and Karen DeBord. 1993. Germ Squirm: Kids and Safe Food Handling, Publication 348-653. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A., and Karen DeBord. 1993. Hurts and Hazards: Kids, Kitchen Accidents, and Safety, Publication 348-655. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann, and Denise Brochetti. 1995. Food Cents, Publication 348-006. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. 1995. ABC's of Feeding Preschoolers, Publication 348-009. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. 1995. Preschoolers' Food Handling Skills-Motor Development, Publication 348-011. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. 1996. Iron Check List, Publication 348-371. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A., and Karen DeBord. 1996. Health Wealth: Kids, Nutrients, and Health, Publication 348-654. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann A. 1997. Herbs and Spices, Publication 348-907. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
Hertzler, Ann. 1999. Nourishing Children with Books, Publication 348-950. [Blacksburg, Va.]: Virginia Cooperative Extension.
The following publications were removed from Series IV: Project/Subject Files and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
American Home Economics Association. 1980, Handbook of Food Preparation. 8th Edition. Washington, D.C. American Home Economics Association.
United States. 1977. Average Weight of a Measured Cup of Various Foods, no. 41. Home Economics Research Report. Washington, D.C.: The Department.
United States. 1990. Food Buying Guide for Child Nutrition Programs. [Washington, D.C.]: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, Food and Nutrition Service.
United States. 1975. Food Yields Summarized by Different Stages of Preparation, no. 102. Agriculture Handbook. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Dept. of Agriculture.
The following VHS tapes were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Special Collections Media Collection:
A Crash Course on Calcium. 1997. Washington, D.C.: National Fluid Milk Processor Promotion Board.
McDonald's Nutrition Information Center, and Society for Nutrition Education. 1993. What's On Your Plate. Oak Brook, IL: McDonald's Nutrition Information Center, McDonald's Corp. (2 copies)
Index Terms
Persons:
Hertzler, Ann A., 1935-2014
Subjects:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; History of Food and Drink; Faculty; Ann Hertzler Children's Cookbooks and Nutrition Literature Collection; Virginia Cooperative Extension Service
Contents List
- Series I: Curriculum Vita and Biographical Information, 1974-2001
  - CV, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards, 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Graduations, Conferences, Events), 1974-2000 (bulk, 1995-2000) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (CHRE Culinary Committee), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Peacock-Harper Culinary Friends Events), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (Newspaper), 1981, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Hertzler Publications, 1971-2000
  - Subseries A: Articles, 1966-2001
    - Articles, 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Bibliography
      Reed, Mary Frances, Ann Hertzler, and Alice Rohweder. "Planning a Foreign Study Program." Journal of Home Economics 58, no. 2 (February 1966): 100-102.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Helen L. Anderson. "Food Guides in the United States." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 64, no. 1 (January 1974): 19-28.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Carol Owen. "Sociologic Study of Food Habits--A Review." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 69 (October 1976): 377-381.
      Stegeman, Barbara, Jan Macey, Judy Hoedel, Delbert Smith, and Ann Hertzler. "Dietetic Students Study Prison Diets." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 69 (December 1976): 649-651.
      Hertzler, Ann A., William Yamanaka, Carol Nenninger, and Areva Abernathy. "Iron Status and Family Structure of Teenage Girls in a Low-Income Area." Home Economics Research Journal 5, no. 2 (December 1976): 92-99.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Loretta W. Hoover. "Development of Food Tables and Use with Computers." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 70, no.1 (January 1977): 20-31.
      Graham, Dee M., and Ann A. Hertzler. "Why Enrich or Fortify Foods?" Journal of Nutrition Education 9, no. 4 (October-December 1977): 166-168.
      Burt, Jill Vornauf, and Ann A. Hertzler. "Parental Influence on the Child's Food Preference." Journal of Nutrition Education 10, no. 3 (July-September 1978): 127-128.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and C. Edwin Vaughan. "The Relationship of Family Structure and Interaction to Nutrition." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 74, no. 1: 23-27.
      Foley, Cynthia, Ann A. Hertzler, and Helen L. Anderson. "Attitudes and Food Habits--A Review." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 75, no. 1 (July 1979): 13-18.
    - Articles, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Hertzler, Ann A. "Obesity--Impact of the Family." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 79, no. 5 (November 1981): np.
      Hertzler, Ann A., Patricia M. Randolph, Jennifer S. Morris, Lynn C. Shuchman, and Cheryl B. Wiles. "Evaluating a Nutrition and Dental Health Conference." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 80 (February 1980): 154-156.
      Hertzler, Ann A., Noa Wenkam, and Bluebell Standal. "Classifying Cultural Food Habits and Meanings." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 80, no. 5 (May 1982): np.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Robert S. Schulman. "Employed Women, Dieting, and Support Groups." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 82, no. 2 (February 1983): 153-158.
      Hertzler, Ann A. "Recipes and Nutrition Education." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 83, no. 4 (October 1983): 466-471.
      Hertzler, Ann A. "Children's Food Patterns--A Review: I. Food Preferences and Feeding Problems." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 83, no. 5 (November 1983): 551-554.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Vera J. Wall. "University Home Economics Programs in the United States: A Survey of International Involvement." Home Economics Research Journal 12, no. 3 (March 1984): 420-432.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Carol Owen. "Culture, Families, and the Change Process--A Systems Approach." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 84, no. 5 (May 1984): 535-543.
      Hertzler, Ann A. "A Systems Approach to Information Processing in Families: A Model for Nutrition Educators." In Home Economics Teacher Education: Knowledge, Technology, and Family Change, 146-165. Bloomington, IL: Bennett & McKnight Publishing Co., 1984.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Joanne Pearson. "Applied Nutrition Communicating Information Through Recipes." Illinois Teacher (March/April 1985): 158-159.
    - Articles, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Novascone, Mary Ann, and Ann A. Hertzler. "Perception of Nutrition Density and Information Links of College Students." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 86, no. 1 (January 1986): 94-95.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Thomas R. McAnge, Jr. "Development of an Iron Checklist to Guide Food Intake." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 86, no. 6 (June 1986): 782-786.
      Hertzler, Ann A., Jean C. Robbins, and Shirley W. Walton. "Assessing Nutrition Education Needs of Office Workers." Journal of Nutrition Education 18, no. 5 (1986): 207-210.
      DeMicco, Frederick J., and Ann A. Hertzler. "Evaluation of a Nutrition Expo for College Students." Journal of Nutrition Education 18. no. 22B (1986): np.
      Torisky, Danielle M., Ann A, Hertzler, and Julien M. Axelson. "A Game to Measure Food Consumption Patterns of Preschool Children." Journal of Nutrition Education 20, no. 22A (1988): np.
      Torisky, Danielle M., Ann A. Hertzler, Janet M. Johnson, James F. Keller, Patricia A. M. Hodges, and Betty S. Mifflin. "Virginia EFNEP Homemakers' Dietary Improvement and Relation to Selected Family Factors." Journal of Nutrition Education 21, no.6 (December 1989): 249-258.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Robert B. Frary. "Food Behavior of College Students." Adolescence 24, no. 94 (Summer 1989): 349-356.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Robert B. Frary. "Effect of Instruction and Family Attributes on Iron Intake of Expanded Food and Nutrition Education Program Homemakers." Topics in Clinical Nutrition 4, no. 1 (January 1989): 27-35.
      Hertzler, Ann A. "Preschoolers' Food Handling Skills--Motor Development." Journal of Nutrition Education 21, no. 100C (1989): np.
    - Articles, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Hertzler, Ann A. "International Perspective of Cross-Cultural Education Programmes in Nutrition." Journal of the Home Economics Association of Australia 22, no. 1 (March 1990): 9-11.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Cynthia Spurr. "Health for All by the Year 2000--Do Home Economists Make a Difference in What People Are Eating?" Journal of the Home Economics Association of Australia 22, no. 2 (June 1990): 40-42.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Ingolf Grün. "Potential Nutrition Messages in Magazines Read by College Students." Adolescence 25, no. 99 (Fall 1990): 717-724.
      Johnston, Pauline, and Ann A. Hertzler. "Elderly Food Ways." Journal of the Home Economics Association of Australia 22, no. 4 (December 1990): 111-114.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Iva Mary Hopkins. "Nutrition Education and Political Participation." Topics in Clinical Nutrition 5, no. 1 (January 1990): 39-46.
      Hertzler, Ann A. "Review of Nutrition Education Programs for Preschoolers." Topics in Clinical Nutrition 5, no. 4 (October 1990): 35-46.
      Hertzler, Ann A. "A Review of Methods to Research Nutrition Knowledge and Dietary Intake of Preschoolers." Topics in Clinical Nutrition 6, no. 1 (December 1990): 1-9.
    - Articles, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Jacqueline M. Newman. "Integrating International Issues with Home Economics Subject Matter." Home Economics Research Journal 19, no. 3 (March 1991): 259-265.
      Baghurst, Katrine I., Ann A. Hertzler, Sally J. Record, and Cynthia Spurr. "The Development of a Simple Dietary Assessment and Education Tool for Use by Individuals and Nutrition Educators." Journal of Nutrition Education 24, no. 4 (July/August 1992): 165-172.
      Hertzler, Ann A., and Robert B. Frary. "Dietary Status and Eating Out in Practices of College Students." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 92, no. 7 (July 1992): np.
      Tang, Wylie, Ann A. Hertzler, and Daisy Stewart. "Survey of Kitchen Equipment Usage, Kitchen Accidents, and Kitchen Safety Awareness of Four-Year-Olds." Journal of Nutrition Education 24, no. 6 (November/December 1992): 316-319.
      Hertzler, Ann A., Juanita Bowens, and Steve Hull. "Preschoolers' Reporting of Food Habits." Journal of the American Dietetic Association 93, no. 10 (October 1993): 1159-1161.